Jim Corbett Collection 1960-1995
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Jim Corbett Collection 1960-1995
MS 502
Corbett, Jim, 1933-
The Jim Corbett Collection documents Corbett's work spanning the early sixties to the mid-nineties, with the bulk of the collection taking place in the 1980s. The content covers personal letters to his wife to research material for the Sanctuary Movement, but a majority of the content are his writings from his books to essays and thoughts. Unpublished essays and an El Salvador License plate are also contained in this collection.
6 Linear ft.
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection
Biographical Note
James A. Corbett (1933-2001) was a rancher, writer, philosopher, and humanitarian. Born in Wyoming, he was educated at Harvard in philosophy before settling in the Southwest where he was a rancher until arthritis made it impossible for him to do a majority of the work involved. In the early 60s he turned Quaker; at this time he was also involved in protesting the Vietnam War.
In the early 80s he learned of the treatment of Central American Refugees both in their home countries but also by federal officials in the United States and began to smuggle them across the U.S.-Mexico border. He considered this act one of civil duty, and shepherded hundreds of refugees to the United States and with the help of Reverend John Fife of the Southside Presbyterian Church in Tucson, AZ, he began the Sanctuary Movement, which established sanctuaries for these refugees in churches, beginning in Tucson but quickly growing larger across the country.
In 1985 Corbett was one of eleven defendants in the Arizona Sanctuary Trial, and one of the three acquitted. After this trial, Corbett continued his work smuggling refugees, claiming that they set the schedule and he would continue to bring them across the border as long as they continued coming. Corbett argued that what he was doing was not civil disobedience, but civil initiative to help uphold asylum laws.
As a writer and philosopher Corbett spoke about errantry, subsistence and covenanting. His first book, Goatwalking, was published in 1991. In the 90s he was primarily involved with the Quakers and remained so until his death in 2001 from a rare brain disease. He is survived by his wife, Pat Corbett.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into eight series
Series I: Writings 1980-1995
Subseries 1: Goatwalking
Subseries 2: Essays and Speeches
Series II: Sanctuary 1980-1990
Subseries 1: Correspondence
Subseries 2: Research
Subseries 3: Legal
Subseries 4: Newsclippings
Subseries 5: Outreach
Series III: John Longenecker Film 1984-1986
Series IV: Animals and Ranging 1991-1994
Series V: Friends 1984-1992
Series VI: Meetings and Minutes 1989-1992
Series VII: Correspondence 1960-1995
Series VIII: Miscellaneous 1976-1995
Scope and Content Note
This collection is comprised of Jim Corbett’s writings, correspondence and research, primarily his book Goatwalking and his work with the Sanctuary Movement in the 1980s. A bulk of the writing is preliminary drafts with editor’s notes, and the remainder is small print run pamphlets and unpublished essays, including his thoughts and reflections on the Sanctuary Movement. Most of the material dealing with the Sanctuary movement is research and background, with some correspondence and some trial outlines from his trial in 1986. The small remainder of the collection includes meeting notes, his private correspondence ranging from the early sixties to the mid-nineties, and details of the film rights for his story.
Included in Series VIII: Miscellaneous is a license plate from El Salvador, and a short typed story of unknown origin.
Access Terms
Sanctuary movement -- Arizona -- Tucson
Spiritual life -- Quaker authors
Simplicity -- Religious aspects -- Christianity
Goats -- Sonoran Desert
Container List
- Series I: Writings, 1980-1992
  - Subseries 1: Goatwalking.
    - Introductory 1, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Introductory 2, Unitdate (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Draft 1, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Draft 2, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Draft 3, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Dead Matter 1, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Dead Matter 2, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Dead Matter 3, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Dead Matter 4, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Chapter 5, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Additional Manuscript Material, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Financials, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Photos of Corbett, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Newsclippings, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Newsclippings, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Subseries 2: Essays and Speeches
    - Heifer Project, Project Bookburners, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Pamphlets, 1980, 1986, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Sanctuary, 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - The Sanctuary Church, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Sanctuary on the Faultline, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - The Burro Book, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - The Diagnosis of Quixote Madness, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - The View from the Border of Cochise, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Ahmisa and Social Conscience, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Poetry, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Notebook, Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series II: Sanctuary, 1980-1990
  This series is arranged by subseries by subject, then by rough chronology
  - Subseries 1: Correspondence
    - White House, , 1983-1984 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Letters of Support for the Defendents, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - INS, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - INS, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 2: Research
    - Borders and Crossings 1, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Borders and Crossings 2, , 1982 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous, 1981-2001 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Statements and Remarks, 1982, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Research, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - TEC, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - TEC, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Geneva Convention Toward Salvadoran Refugees, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Chicago Religious Task Force on CA, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Butler, A Bates Speech, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Arizona Sanctuary Fund, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Miscellaneous 1 of 2, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Miscellaneous 2 of 2, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Report: Mesa Grande Repatriation, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Mexico (Spanish contents), 1987 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Conference Alliance for the Sanctuary Movement, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Refugees at Risk, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Judith McBride, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - National Sanctuary Defense Fund, Undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Archdiocese of Hermosillo Action Plan, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - A Theological Analysis of the Sanctuary Movement, Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - International League for Human Rights, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - The Politics of Sanctuary, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 3: Legal
    - Affadavits, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Convictions Outline, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Immigration Reform and Control Act, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - INS, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Testimony of the Center for Constitutional Rights, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Volunteer Interpreter, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - INS, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Training in Immigration Law, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Maps, Undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Writings, Undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Subseries 4: Newsclippings
    - Newsclippings, 1982-1986 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Newsclippings, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Newsclippings, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Newsclippings, 1986-1991 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Newsclippings, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Subseries 5: Outreach
    - Speeches, Undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Event Flyers and Programs, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Border Network, Undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Political Cartoons, Undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Series III: John Longenecker Film, 1984-1986
  This series is arranged in rough chronological order
  - Film Outline, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Research Book 1, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Research Book 2, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Transcript, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - 1985 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Film Rights, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Series IV: Animals and Ranging, 1991-1994
  - Rangeland Resources, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - animals Foundation, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Natural Resource Conservancy District, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - The Nature Conservancy, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - The Humane Society (1), 1994 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - The Humane Society (2), 1994 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - CRIA, Undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Series V: Friends, 1984-1982
  - Quaker Publications, 1984-1986 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - American Friends Service Committee, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Pima Friends, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Peace Pilgrim, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Series VI: Meetings and Minutes, 1989-1992
  - 8th Annual Human Rights Award Ceremony, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Intermountain Yearly Meetings, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Quick Response, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Goat and Garden Group, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Goat and Garden Group Financials, Undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Series VII: Correspondence, 1960-1992
  - 1960s, 1960-1969 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - 1980s (1 of 3), 1980-1989 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - 1980s (2 of 3), 1980-1989 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - 1980s (3 of 3), 1980-1989 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Address and Letter to Senator Simpson, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - 1992 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - To Pat Corbett, Undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Series VIII: Miscellaneous, 1976-1989
  This series is arranged in rough chronological order,except for the last folder which is a dated object
  - Tohono O'odam Report, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Jubilee Partners, Undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Unknown Writing, Undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Cochise College Censorship in Library, Undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Printed Excerpts from Carl Schmidtt, Undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - El Salvador License, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 30)